Welcome to 2026 release wave 1 of
business central launch edition. This
session is about enhanced IT audit
reporting.
So why invest in this? Well, we got
first of all we got feedback the
internal controls and the reporting on
that was kind of hard in business
central. So we try to make that easier
and in general make it easier for the IT
admin to uh to on on things such as
permissions, approvals, user management
se so second value add here is that we
learned that for some larger
organizations it can be quite difficult
for it to get access to the IP system.
problem is that it needs to perform
internal control, reporting and
compliance. Um, so for them to actually
get the data out of the AP system would
need to ask controllers to to get
reports and hand it over. So we thought
maybe we can add APIs to business
central so that it can get access to
APIs and do their own internal controls
reporting with copilot studio agents or
with power powerbi. In this session,
we're going to talk start in analyzing
permissions and new ways of analyzing
approvals, go through user management,
and end in permission and approval APIs,
new APIs that are coming in 28.x.
The first new feature is a page where
you can analyze permissions across
probably every aspect of uh of things.
And this page is called permission
overview. And basically it allows you
either to filter on objects uh object
type, object ID, permission set scope or
which app things are coming from. That's
one way of filtering down. Also in the
fact box uh on this page you can see for
each permission set which security
groups does include this and also which
users have this permission set. This
data is valuable like this in itself.
But when you then take this list into
analysis mode, then you can you can do
some really compelling analysis. For
instance, in this case here, I've just
grouped by object name and delete
whether you can delete. And suddenly you
have an overview of which permission
sets allow deletion on which tables.
Right? So that's just one way of
pivoting this data. Here's a different
pivot. What does this permission allow?
So here we are grouping on permission
set and then object name and then you
can see then across delete, modify,
execute and so on kind of what
permission set allows certain operations
to which objects. This also highlights
or showcase the screenshot, the new
feature in analysis mode where you can
add descriptions to your analysis views
and then they showcase as tool tips when
you hover over these.
Now, there are tons of things you could
show with that permission overview, but
I would rather that you play with it and
and get an understanding and and and
hopefully let us know where it's
valuable and if there are places where
we could do uh better.
Now one thing is is analyzing
permissions then it's uh it's cousin in
auditing is approvals or workflow like
so permissions is who can do what where
approvals is who are who are allowed to
approve what and to which limits. So
here in 28.x so this is not for the
April release hopefully in one of the m
like miners 28.1 28.2 two uh two new
overviews, approval user overview and
approval entry overview. Let's take a
look at the first one.
So um with this page you can simply
navigate through the different types of
workflows on the top of the screen and
below you can see who are allowed to
approve what with which limits across
these. So before this overview you would
need to go into each type of workflow
and do this analysis. Now you can just
do it one by one and hopefully this
frees up a lot of time in case you need
to answer an auditor who are allowed to
approve what and to which limits.
A different overview across all
workflows is the approval entry
overview. I don't have any data to show
you but this page shows you across types
of approvals uh whether it's posted or
not apposted. You can kind of see get
that overview in one screen. And similar
to the permissions overview here, you
can also take this page into analysis
mode and then perform all sorts of
pivots that in themselves would feel
like different reports on this data set.
Now when we looked at the code for the
approval of workflow system we also um
just made sure that it is we leave it in
a better state than when we we came
there. uh which means all the approval
pages now appear in advanced tellme with
uh teaching tips with good descriptions
and uh and and also that when you open
the help pane for all these pages they
have uh inclient help and correct links
to the documentation. So just hopefully
if you don't if you're not like super
familiar with this part of business
central just the inclined help
experience and all of these um help uh
teaching tips will help you to quicker
to get an understanding of the different
objects.
Just some examples here posted approval
entries approval request entries and
approval entries all got teaching tips.
They surface in advanced tell me and in
in uh when you hover when you click the
captions or with if you open the help
pane.
All right. In version 28 we added the
ability from A code to add analysis
views. So we're also applying this to
the base uh to the to the base app to
the application. And within auditing we
have added um um these analysis tabs in
in two lists. One is change log entries.
to the other one is the users lists and
that means that you will in 28.x X when
this is surfacing for instance here on
the change lock entries the two mini
reports so quote unquote reports are uh
data changes by table and field. So here
in this report, it's not a report, it's
just an analysis tab. Uh but you can see
it's grouped by uh table field. And then
if you if you go down to customer
address, you can then see everything
that happened to the customer uh table
on the address field and by whom.
Similarly, the other report that we
added to change lock is who changed to
what data when. So in this case here you
can see we're grouping by user ID and
then based on the user you can say see
everything that that user changed if
change log has been enabled for these uh
tables and fields. Another way to use
this uh report is that uh for agents
that are performing in this things in
your business in your in your system
business central environment for things
where you have enabled change lock you
can see the agent users similar to a
normal user. So this is also kind of an
audit log of uh what was changed in the
system by agents. You can you can use it
for that as well.
For the user table, we have these two uh
user by status. So, it's a very simple
whether users are enabled or not and
what license type they have. So, just a
very quick overview of that. It's a mini
report of enabled or disabled users. And
the other report is users by license
type. So, you can kind of see depending
on uh whether you're onrem or or in the
online version uh the license type and
then which users have one or the other.
So permissions, approvals and now um
since we were kind of working in in this
area, we thought let's also do something
to the user management experience. So we
have a couple of uh smaller and larger
improvements here. Um I think smaller
but if you collectively I think this is
lifting the user management experience.
This is also coming in 28.x. So you just
wait to to have to wait uh one or two
months to get this. So here is the users
list the nor normal lists uh for where
you see anything related to users. Here
we are adding the last login date and
also inact we we are computing inactive
days. So just on the users list here you
can see if you have inactive users um
and how long time they have been active
or if they are uh in the system. You
could easily use this on go live. So you
can just see here if people are actually
testing. If they said they tested on
Friday and they never logged in, well
they didn't test. There's also in the
fact box new information on the user
setup things like allow posting from
register time settings uh things from
the user settings uh is is shown here as
well for the given user. So that's just
instead of needing to navigate you can
just see that in the fact box. Then for
a given user, we added navigation links
to user settings, approval user setup
and user setup all related to the user.
But in the past, you couldn't navigate
from here. You would actually need to
open that page and and do things. So
just making it easier to manage all
users in all aspects of what a user
needs to be managed on.
And then I think two years ago we added
this user detailed view which is kind of
similar to this page but it's
constructed in a way that allows us to
do normal analysis mode operations which
then for implementation details the
normal users list is is it's hard for us
to do things there. So let me open that.
For this one we added a few things. We
added some different views on this
table. So you can see the user detail
view. We also added the last login date
and inactive days. But now you can also
uh see things like users with super
active users or inactive 7, 30 or 90
days. So make it very easy to prefilter
on certain of these scenarios. And of
course if you then take that list uh
here's an example of inactive 30 days.
You can also take this list with this
view, filter it to something and then
take that into analysis mode and add a
further um analysis views on that. All
right. And the final
part of this um work are the new
permissions uh sorry the new APIs. So
the reason we are investing in APIs of
course it's broadening the API surface
for business central is helping copilot
studio powerbi
um power automate things like that. Um
in this particular case the the business
case or the reason for this is that we
learned in probably larger organizations
there's kind of a natural barrier or
physical barrier between the IT
department who traditionally own the
internal controls like who have access
to what like the auditing of users and
all of that and then over here this the
you can think of these as the technical
system owners of the ERP system or
business central and over here in the
finance department. They're typically
the system owners or the operational
part of the the organization are the the
the operational system owners of
Business Central. And then if the IT
guys don't have can't get access to the
EIP system, if they need to do their
internal control, they need to ask
someone over here to run reports, send
data back and forth and so on. So what
if we could do something else? Um and
that's why we are introducing these APIs
and the APIs on workflow or approvals.
So that with these APIs if in the
business central administrator give the
IT or a user in IT only access to these
uh APIs they will be able to set up
agents where they can ask who can do
what or they can uh take these this data
and load it into their own PowerBI
reports and kind of do all their
internal controls uh that way. So that's
the reasoning for these the the
different APIs are as follows. So we
have one on permission sets this one and
all of these APIs are read only. This
one you can you can query all permission
sets but then navigate from there
through the access control subpage to
also get which users or security groups
are linked to a given permission set.
Basically, if you go back to this
presentation in the permissions
overview, that's the UI. These are the
the API version of of uh of that
overview.
Expanded permission sets allows you to
also get the app table. So it expanded
permissions table and then the the app
name added um security groups shows you
security group but also uh subpage
through uh to the access control to see
uh the linked permission sets and
security group members for security
groups.
User permission pay API shows the users
but then also navigate from a from users
into user permission sets to see who um
what are permissions assigned to users
and then finally uh the access control
you have heard about that already uh
this is uh the access control records
for for all the other uh APIs you can
navigate to this from the other pages
similarly also in 28.x X the permission
APIs are also coming in 28.x
Same thing for approval APIs. I call it
approval but these are kind of workflow
APIs. So here the workflows API will
allow you to navigate all workflows and
then from there you can you can uh from
a given workflow you can go to workflow
steps in workflow steps that shows all
the steps for a specific workflow. You
can navigate from a step into the
workflow response option and that's the
next API that then show all the step
argument records approver type approver
ID and so on for all these APIs similar
with these compared to what permissions.
So all of these APIs is kind of the API
version of the new pages on a on
approvals. Um so just opening up for
those same types of reports but now with
APIs so you can create recreate those
reports without having like a login UI
access to business central workflow
approvers uh list every workflow and
approver type and and limit and then um
then you can also navigate the users if
it's a workflow group or specific
approver
user setup again show it. This one shows
the detail uh approval chain, direct
approval or first qualified approval
workflows for a given user. And finally,
approval entries will list all approval
entry record. So you can kind of get
that uh who did what when or who
approved what when uh type of report. It
comes both with a normal and with posted
approval entries.
So that's it. Before we close uh close
the presentation, if you want to learn
more, go to our security guide
aka.ms/bcsecurity.
And in here uh we have updated
everything to these new objects, APIs
and so on. As well as uh we also updated
the security guide with um specifically
for different types of scen security
scenarios. Um so a completely new
article for that. We took all we learned
from giving security and auditing
sessions at conferences plus the work
that was done internally in Microsoft to
harden um things around business central
internally and part of this secure
future initiative across Microsoft and
kind of applied that into the publicly
facing security guide. So go check that
out. Hopefully you can learn something
that can help you harden the systems
both from within and uh and with the
external boundaries.
Specifically for the APIs, your friend
here to learn more is aka.ms/bc
integration. This is the landing page
for everything related to integrations
that are built on APIs. So uh here uh
you can find under APIs all the new APIs
uh will be documented here when they
surface in business central.
If this is interesting for you maybe a
related session for the new APIs also
for all the documents types will might
also be of interest. So uh so there's a
link for that presentation down here in
the description.
And that's it before I close the session
recording here. If you uh don't know the
general business central resources, stay
put for another couple of minutes. If
you already know all of this, then uh
this is the end. Thank you so much for
watching. Thanks for being part of the
Business Central launch edition and have
a great day. Bye.
We have compiled a number of general
resources that we believe are key both
for partners but also uh business
central customers. Most some of these
are partner some of them are also for
customers. So the first one is called
aka.ms/bcall.
This is a partner resource for that
contains lists of every other AKA link
that is needed for you to understand
anything about both the business central
product but also processes around it. We
call these aka links because they are
called aka.ms and then for/ something.
And with business central links we all
always prefix with bc and then
something. The next one is uh our uh
partner network uh social media for for
business central partners Viva. Viva
engage. So ak.ms/bc
viva engage is where you go and interact
with other partners. It's not open for
customers. So this is where you can ask
questions, interact with a product
group, interact with with with each
other um in a in a closed network.
Second link, a third link is for both
partners and customers. We are called
office hours. So office hours is
something we do once or twice a month
from the product group engaging with the
community about new features or things
we want to discuss. Aka.msbc
office hours is the is the place where
you go to find out about upcoming
events. These are recorded. I believe
the recordings are available only to
partners but the live events are
available to customers as well. Fourth
link is YouTube, our YouTube channel.
I'll talk about that uh in the next
slide and LinkedIn in the next slide. Uh
and then finally uh for for Microsoft
partners, the BC ak.msbc
partner portal is where you get um a lot
of the resources as a partner such as
compete decks, uh pitch decks and a lot
of other resources
for LinkedIn. This is our product
group's uh LinkedIn profile. We have 30K
or more followers. So both partners and
customers, this is the place where we
from the product group put in news and
small bits of information outside the
quote unquote official channel. So
follow us on on LinkedIn to learn what's
happening right now um in in this in the
around the product. Um and then uh also
on our YouTube channel, this is where
you're probably watching this aka.msbc
YouTube. We put in not only these launch
editions twice a year, but also co-pilot
and AI video shorts, tips and tricks,
technical deep dives under the hood. Uh
we even have this watch cooking where we
put little nuggets of of videos out for
new features that are even coming in on
the YouTube channel before uh they're
coming in the release notes. So watch uh
and maybe bookmark us on YouTube and
also notice all the playlists. So the
the content is also organized in areas
not only all the videos. So if you have
an area that has special interests such
as analytics um you can find an a
playlist and kind of see all the content
related to that. And that's it. That is
truly it. We won't uh there would be no
more. So, thank you for watching all the
way to the end and again have a great
day. Thank you.